Speaker: Here is a standard pack of playing cards:
fifty-two cards, four suits – spades, clubs, diamonds, hearts – twelve picture cards, two jokers.
Most people are familiar with these cards. But what do you know about their history and their uses?
The first playing cards originated in Asia, probably in China in the ninth century.
Between the ninth and the fourteenth centuries they travelled west across the world,
through India, Persia, and Egypt, to Europe.
The early cards looked different from the ones we know today,
and the suits were different in different countries, for example, cups, swords, leaves, bells, and roses.
The picture cards were all male figures, the king, the jack, and a soldier on a horse.
From the sixteenth century, the French pack of fifty-two cards that we know today became the most common.
Its design was simple and therefore cheap to print. Why are there fifty-two cards?
And why four suits…and twelve picture cards?
No one knows for sure, but an interesting theory is that the fifty-two cards represent the fifty-two weeks in a year,
the four suits represent the four seasons (spring, summer, autumn, and winter),
and the twelve picture cards represent the twelve months of the year.
The highest picture card is the king. On the king card, the king always has a sword or an axe.
The kings also always have moustaches, except for the king of hearts, who sometimes doesn’t have one.
The second highest picture card is the queen. The French introduced the queen instead of the soldier on a horse.
On the queen card, the queen always has a flower in her hand.
In English packs of cards, the jack was originally called the knave.
However, because the initials of the picture cards appear in the corner of each card,
and there was already a ‘K’ for ‘king’, knave became ‘jack’.
The jokers were first added to the pack in the eighteen fifties.
They soon became a standard part of the pack, and in some games they are ‘wild cards’, that is,
they can be any card. Playing cards quickly became very popular.
This was because previously most games were for two players.
Card games were ideal for lots of different numbers of players, and were especially popular with women.
The international fifty-two-card pack is still very popular all over the world with people of all ages:
easy children’s games, games for one person, and serious games like Bridge or Canasta.
But playing cards are not only for games.
Although there are special fortune-telling card packs, like tarot cards,
the standard pack was also a very popular way to tell people’s fortune in the eighteenth, nineteenth, and twentieth centuries.
The four suits represent four themes: spades are about challenges or difficulties,
hearts are about feelings and relationships, clubs are about positive things, diamonds are about money.
Each number and picture card also has a special meaning.
You can have all sorts of fun with cards in many different ways.